Guide to Culinary Ephemera: Flour Products, Leavening Agents, and Baked Goods ams.0058
University of Michigan Library (Special Collections Research Center)
- Leavening Agents
  - Box 47.
    Wing, Hannah.
    Wilson, Mary A.
    Splint, Sarah Field, 1883-1959.
    Horsford, Eben Norton, 1818-1893.
    Becker, Bertha M.
    Batchelder, Ann.
    Baker, Elizabeth Ann.
    Rumford Chemical,
    Rumford Baking Powder Co. (Terre Haute, Ind.)
    - Household hand book / compiled by Lily Haxworth Wallace. 36 p., circa 1910s (Box 47, Folder 1)
      Item [1] promotes Rumford baking powder, made from Professor E.N. Horsford's phosophate. Contains advertisement for Rumford complete cook book by Lily Haxworth Wallace. Household hints include daily schedule and kitchen conveniences. Cornelius S. Sweetland, President. Marked T 38.
    - Household hand book / compiled by Lily Haxworth Wallace. 36 p., circa 1920s (Box 47, Folder 2)
      Item [2] is similar to [1] except Andrew Fiske, President. Marked T 38.
    - Rumford book on home management / compiled by Hannah Wing. 64 p., circa 1920s (Box 47, Folder 3)
      Item [3] promotes Rumford baking powder. Has recipes to serve 100 and seasoning recommendations. Has same book offer as [1]. Marked E. 96.
    - Rumford Southern recipes / compiled by Mary A. Wilson. 65 p., circa 1920s (Box 47, Folder 4)
      Item [4] promotes Rumford baking powder. Includes color illustrations of serving suggestions. Sections on cakes, breads, icings, pastry, savory recipes, and waffles. Sample recipes: Rumford water biscuit, cracklin bread, and Tennessee black cake. Includes menus for Sunday night suppers. Has same book offer as [1]. Marked X. 94
    - The Rumford way of cookery and household economy / compiled by Janet McKenzie Hill. 68 p., circa 1910s (Box 47, Folder 5)
      Item [5] promotes Rumford baking powder. Includes color illustrations of serving suggestions. Sample recipes: Green corn griddle cakes, entire wheat scones, and prune pie. Has same book offer as [1]. Marked K. 71.
    - A selection of choice recipes: [folded brochure], circa 1920s (Box 47, Folder 6)
      Item [6] promotes Rumford baking powder. Cover illustration of children cooking "playing cook." Six recipes. Has same book offer as [1]. Marked X 95.
    - The Rumford modern methods of cooking / prepared by the House of Sarah Field Splint. 64 p., circa 1922 (Box 47, Folder 7)
      Item [7] promotes Rumford baking powder. Sample recipes: Hermits, lightning cake, and molasses pudding. Has same book offer as [1]. Marked B. 82.
    - Rumford fruit recipes / by Lily Haxworth Wallace. 46 p., 1927 (Box 47, Folder 8)
      Item [8] promotes Rumford baking powder. Mentions book from [1]. Sample recipes: Apple cream pie, banana cream cake, and currant punch. Illustrated serving suggestions. Marked X-96.
    - 24 uses for Rumford all-phosphate baking powder in cooking. [11 p.], 1929 (Box 47, Folder 9)
      Item [9] promotes Rumford baking powder. Tested by Bertha M. Becker, in her laboratory. Uses in cooking as opposed to baking. Sample recipes: Peas, fish cakes, and cottage cheese. Offer for book in [1]. Marked N-101.
    - Attractive meals planned complete: 32 menus, 72 recipes. 56 p., 1931 (Box 47, Folder 10)
      Item [10] promotes Rumford baking powder. Foreword by Ann Batchelder. Illustrations of serving suggestions. Sample recipes: Almond soup, raspberry puffs, and frozen cookies. Marked 0-106.
    - 64 new uses for Rumford all-phosphate baking powder in daily cooking. 29 p., 1932 (Box 47, Folder 11)
      Item [11] is an expanded version of [9]. Sample recipes: Pocahontas filling, soy bean loaf, and mayonnaise dressing. Marked K-104. 1-31.
    - Rumford new use cook book. 4th ed. 32 p., 1935 (Box 47, Folder 12)
      Item [12] is similar to [11]. Full approval from American Medical Association and Goodhousekeeping Bureau. Sample recipes: Parisian apple pie, liver terrapin, and New England shepherd's pie. Illustrated serving suggestions. Marked: M-117.
    - 64 new uses for Rumford all-phosphate baking powder in daily cooking. 32 p., 1932 (Box 47, Folder 13)
      Item [13] is similar to [11]. Has NRA seal on cover. Marked A.108/3/32.
    - Why baking powder, when baking powder, what baking powder?: [folded brochure], circa 1933 (Box 47, Folder 14)
      Item [14] is an offer for New uses recipes. Has three recipes. Marked: A-113-1-33.
    - Cake: good, better, best: which is yours?: [folded brochure], circa 1932 (Box 47, Folder 15)
      Item [15] promotes Rumford baking powder. Has recipe for Plain cake with discussions on why "... cakes misbehave." NRA seal on cover. Marked L-103.
    - Biscuits and biscuits glorified: twenty-one recipes. 16 p., 1941 (Box 47, Folder 16)
      Item [16] promotes Rumford baking powder. Introduction and comments on some recipes by Elizabeth Ann Baker. Illustration of product packaging on back cover.
    - My favorite Rumford recipes. 67 p., 1994 (Box 47, Folder 17)
      Item [17] promotes Rumford baking powder. Sample recipes: Pineapple corn bread, gold cake, and Scotch scones with peaches.
    - Clabber Girl baking book. 19 p., 1934 (Box 47, Folder 18)
      Item [18] promotes Clabber Girl baking powder. Illustrations of period dress, packaging, serving sugestions, and Good housekeeping seal.
    - Clabber Girl recipes: [folded brochure], circa 1930s (Box 47, Folder 19)
      Item [19] promotes Clabber Girl baking powder. Illustration of packaging.
    - Old-fashioned favorites. 81 p., 1991 (Box 47, Folder 20)
      Item [20] promotes Clabber Girl baking powder. Illustrations of serving suggestions. Sample recipes: Candy bar raspberry torte, country scones, and apple crostata.
    - Clabber Girl: now 3 key ingredients have my trusted name: [folded brochure]., circa 1999 (Box 47, Folder 21)
      Item [21] promotes Clabber Girl baking powder, cornstarch, and baking soda. Illustrated product packaging and serving suggestions.
  - Box 48.
    Simpson, A. M., Miss.
    Willis, Leida A.
    Bentley, Mildred Maddocks.
    Miller, Anna Jenness.
    Whiting, F. A.
    Smith, Sydney.
    - Utility and economy in cooking /by Lily Haxworth. 21 p., 1919 (Box 48, Folder 1)
      Item [1] promotes Rumford baking powder. Lilly Haxworth is gold medalist and graduate of National Training School of Cookery, London, England. Includes price list stamp on back cover. Sample recipes: oatmeal gems, queen éclairs, and orange puffs. Cover detached in two pieces. Marked: F-15 10-19.
    - The most desirable to sell: the wholesome Rumford Baking Powder. 1 v. (unpaged), circa 1900 (Box 48, Folder 2)
      Item [2] promotes Rumford baking powder and consists of lined pages for grocery lists. Includes product packaging illustration and no recipes.
    - Rumford: the wholesome baking powder. 8 p., 1907 (Box 48, Folder 3)
      Item [3] promotes Rumford baking powder. Includes illustration of young woman holding sheaves of wheat on front cover, of factory on inside front cover, and medals awarded to manufacturers; history of Rumford Chemical Works, Providence, R.I. and E.N. Horsford, one of the founders in 1859; and list of US and foreign branches. Notes "guaranteed under the food and drugs act, June 30, 1906." Sample recipes: whole wheat bread and crumpets.
    - Rumford cook book. 47 p. "G.13"-Page [1]., circa 1900 (Box 48, Folder 4)
      Item [4] promotes Rumford baking powder. Recipes compiled by Leida A. Willis, principal, Baltimore Cooking School. States "'yeast powder' was the original term for a baking powder." Includes addresses of where to buy, hints for using in baking, index, table of measures, medicinal uses, list of Rumford Chemical Works products, and illustrations of young girl in period dress on cover and of product packaging. Sample recipes: savory stew with dumplings, chocolate nut cake, frost cookies, and breaded tongue with tomato sauce.
    - The Rumford cook book / by Fannie Merritt Farmer. 47, [1] p. "B.22"-Page [1]. "Rumford complete cook book / by Lily Haxworth Wallace" advertisement on page [48]., circa 1900s (Box 48, Folder 5)
      Item [5] promotes Rumford Baking Powder. Includes index; hints on using signed by Fannie Merritt Farmer, principal, Boston Cooking School; table of weights and measures; table of proportions; offer for Rumford complete cook book by Lilly Haxworth Wallace for 10 cards from one pound cans; history of Rumford Chemical Works; and product packaging illustration. Sample recipes: Indian bread, pineapple lemonade, and clams à la Newburg.
    - Rumford receipt book. 20 p., 1908 (Box 48, Folder 6)
      Item [6] promotes Rumford Baking Powder. Includes note from Lilly Haxworth Wallace, the author, on inside front cover; offer for Rumford complete cook book by Wallace for 10 cards from one pound cans; and illustrations of young girl's head on front cover and product packaging on back cover. Notes Rumford Baking Powder does not contain "alum or other unhealthful materials" and explains that phosphates are necessary for health. Sample recipes: fairies cake, pencil rolls, and puff paste.
    - Rumford receipt book. 24 p., circa 1908 (Box 48, Folder 7)
      Item [7] promotes Rumford Baking Powder. Includes note from the author, Mildred Maddocks, author and lecturer at Massachusetts State Board of Agriculture, on inside front cover; offer for Rumford complete cook book by Lily Haxworth Wallace for 10 cards from one pound cans; and illustrations of young girl in period outerwear on front cover and product packaging on back cover. Sample recipes: cornmeal rolls, Parker House rolls, maple caramel cake, and codfish fritters. Cover torn and almost detached.
    - [Rumford receipt book]. 32 p., circa 1908 (Box 48, Folder 8)
      Item [8] promotes Rumford Baking Powder. Includes preface from Henrietta C. Beeks, who compiled the recipes; offer for Rumford complete cook book by Lily Haxworth Wallace (illustration shown) for 10 cards from one pound cans; directions for making ice cream; measuring instructions; illustrations of young girl in period dress holding daffodils on front cover and product packaging on back cover; history of Rumford Chemical works; and index. Sample recipes: Rumford biscuits, Rumford crullers (New England fried cakes), and feather cake.
    - [Rumford receipt book]. 12 p., 1913 (Box 48, Folder 9)
      Item [9] promotes Rumford Baking Powder. Includes illustrations of young girl in period dress holding daffodils on front cover and product packaging on back cover; offer for Rumford complete cook book by Lily Haxworth Wallace (illustration shown) for 10 cards from one pound cans; measuring instructions; and history of Rumford Chemical works. Sample recipes: mahogany cake and lady fingers.
    - Rumford common sense cook book / compiled by Lilly Haxworth Wallace. 64. p., circa 1920 (Box 48, Folder 10)
      Item [10] promotes Rumford Baking Powder. Includes index; measuring instructions; bread and cake baking hints; how to bake with sour milk; baking temperatures table; cooking terms glossary; diagram of semi-formal table setting with menu; offer for Rumford complete cook book by Lily Haxworth Wallace for 10 cards from one pound cans; charts of beef and lamb cuts; meat and poultry cooking hints; vegetable cooking hints and time table; instructions on canning, preserving, and pickling; and auto, picnic, and school lunch menus. Sample recipes: crumb griddle cakes, baked custard, corn flake cookies, toad-in-a-hole, and Spanish meat loaf. 2 copies.
    - Cakes and cookies. 16 p., circa 1920 (Box 48, Folder 11)
      Item [11] promotes Rumford Baking Powder. Includes Count Rumford illustration and Rumford Company Dept. of Home Economics on front cover, substitute measurements for one cup wheat flour, and cake-making instructions. Sample recipes: hot water sponge cake and pound cake. Marked: X 79 1 20.
    - Little book of entrées. 15 p., 1919 (Box 48, Folder 12)
      Item [12] promotes Rumford Baking Powder. Includes Count Rumford illustration and Rumford Company Dept. of Home Economics on front cover, discussion of value of phosphates in food, and offer of one of Little book series for card in cans. Marked: V.86.
    - A selection of choice recipes: [brochure]., 1920 (Box 48, Folder 13)
      Item [13] promotes Rumford Baking Powder. Includes illustrations of grandmother and daughter in period dress and kitchen on front cover ("How's that, Grandma?") and product packaging illustration on back cover. Sample recipe: frosted loaf cake.
    - A wholesome tonic, Horsford's acid phosphate. 8 p., circa 1920s (Box 48, Folder 14)
      Item [14] promotes Horsford's acid phosphate as additive to fruit juice and other beverages for good taste and health. Includes discussion of health benefits; reference to "these days of non-alcoholic beverages"; and illustrations of young woman in sailor blouse on front cover and product packaging on back cover. Sample recipes: strawberry fruit punch, orange phosphate ice, and ginger ale phosphate. Marked: P.49. 2 copies.
    - [Horsford's acid phosphate]: [broadside]., circa 1910s (Box 48, Folder 15)
      Item [15] promotes Horsford's acid phosphate for health benefits. Includes product packaging illustration. Consists of 3 leaflets marked: G.45, B.45 7 14; Q.44.
    - Rumford complete cook book: [postcard]., circa 1920s (Box 48, Folder 16)
      Item [16] promotes Rumford Baking Powder. Postcard with offer for Rumford complete cook book by Lily Haxworth Wallace for 10 cards from one pound cans.
    - A few suggestions for cake of moderate cost / Lily Haxworth. 11 p., 1898 (Box 48, Folder 17)
      Item [17] promotes Rumford Baking Powder for economical cake baking. Includes cake-making hints and reproduction of handwritten testimonial from Anna Jenness Miller, dated April 1898, on back cover. Sample recipes: cheap sponge cake and inexpensive layer cake. Marked: N.-14 7-19.
    - Horsford's bread and pastry cook. 48 p., circa 1890 (Box 48, Folder 18)
      Item [18] promotes improved Horsford's Baking Powder. Includes illustrations of Count Rumford on front cover and product packaging on back cover; glued-in notice that since printing it has been shown that less Horsford's is needed due to its greater strength; biscuit recipe without shortening laid in, marked: E-II; addresses of where to buy; hints for using in baking; index; table of measures and cooking times; testimonials from "eminent physicians, chemists, and experts"; and list of Rumford Chemical Works products on inside back cover. Marked: N-10.
    - The 1883 Horsford almanac & cook book. 48 p. (Box 48, Folder 19)
      Item [19] promotes Horsford self-raising bread preparation and other products. Includes product packaging illustration showing patent dates; Count Rumford illustration on front cover and elegant artwork featuring a peacock on back cover; where to buy; general directions on use; medicinal benefits; postage rates; 1880 US census data; jokes, including Negro dialect speech on the revised testament; illustrations of children, mostly girls, in period dress engaged in seasonal and cooking activities, signed by F.A. Whiting, Boston; and list of Rumford Chemical Works products. Sample recipes: centennial rolls, Yorkshire pudding to serve with meat, and scones.
    - The new Horsford's bread and pastry cook / compiled by Miss A.M. Simpson. 48 p., circa 1890 (Box 48, Folder 20)
      Item [20] promotes Horsford's baking powder. Includes illustrations of Count Rumford on front cover and product packing on back cover; where to buy; table of measures and cooking time; index; note tipped in that teaspoon should be slightly rounded; and list of Rumford Chemical Works products. Sample recipes: hominy or rice griddle cakes, currant cake, and peach meringue pie. Marked: T-14.
    - Rumford everyday cook book for the housekeeper and student / compiled by Mary A. Wilson, Lily Haxworth Wallace, Janet McKenzie Hill. 68 p., circa 1910 (Box 48, Folder 21)
      Item [21] promotes Rumford baking powder. Includes index; hints on baking; principles of food selection; vegetable nutrition and cookery; uses of stale bread and biscuits; illustrations of product packaging and serving suggestions; Sunday supper menus; and offer for Rumford complete cookbook for 10 cards from one pound cans. Sample recipes: orange feather cake, Rumford cheese muffins, boiling water pastry, and plum pudding. Marked: F-94.
    - Rumford everyday cook book for the housekeeper and student / compiled by Mary A. Wilson, Lily Haxworth Wallace, Janet McKenzie Hill. 64 p., circa 1910 (Box 48, Folder 22)
      Item [22] is similar to [21] except with 4 fewer pages and in poorer condition. Marked: U-90.
    - Some of the difficulty of liquor prosecutions: [brochure]., circa 1890s (Box 48, Folder 23)
      Item [23] is a tract published by Young Men's Christian Temperance Union of Providence on the difficulty of liquor prosecutions. Promotes Horsford's baking powder with product packaging illustration and public endorsments from cooking authorities.
    - The Horsford cook book. 36 p., circa 1880s (Box 48, Folder 24)
      Item [24] promotes Rumford Chemical Works products. Includes list of products; index; history of Prof. Horsford's bread preparation; testimonials attributed to eminent physicians, chemists, and experts; baking hints; medicinal uses; cover illustrations of serving suggestions and product packaging; and offer for picture hung in stores for four labels. Sample recipes: milk bread, oyster patties, hominy muffins, and Tennessee corn bread.
    - Das Horsford's koch-buch. 32 p., circa 1880s (Box 48, Folder 25)
      Item [25] is in German and promotes Horsford's baking powder. Includes list of Rumford Chemical Works products, history of baking powder, attributed testimonials, medicinal uses, where to obtain the products, and list of awards.
    - The Horsford almanac and cook book, 1879. 48 p. (Box 48, Folder 26)
      Item [26] promotes Horsford's bread preparation and other Rumford Chemical Works products. Includes list of products and advertisements interspersed with almanac information and recipes; illustration of girl in period dress on back cover; recipe in rhyme titled Sydney Smith's receipt for salad dressing; and recommendation of Marion Harland's cook books. Stamped: Kimball Bros. & Co., Sandford, ME.
    - Rumford, the "wholesome" baking powder. 1 v. (unpaged), circa 1908 (Box 48, Folder 27)
      Item [27] promotes Rumford baking powder. Includes history of Rumford Chemical works and offer for Rumford complete cook book by Lilly Haxworth Wallace for 10 cards from one pound cans. Recipes by Lily Haxworth Wallace. Sample recipes: coffee layer cake and soft corn bread. Marked: J-48.
    - Biscuits and biscuits glorified: twenty-one recipes. 16 p., 1941 (Box 48, Folder 28)
      Item [28] promotes Rumford baking powder. Includes introduction signed by Elizabeth Ann Baker, hints on making biscuits, brief comment from her on each recipe, product packaging illustration on back cover, and index. Sample recipes: Dutch apple cake with cinnamon cream, hamburger roll-ups, and orange rolls.
    - Magic muffins: twenty-three recipes. 15 p., 1941 (Box 48, Folder 29)
      Item [29] promotes Rumford baking powder. Includes introduction signed by Elizabeth Ann Baker; hints on making muffins and quick-breads; product packaging illustration on back cover; index, and laid-in offer for others in series of 4, each for one cook book card found inside cans. Sample recipes: lemon tea muffins and quick coffee cake with streusel topping.
    - New sugarless recipes from the Rumford kitchens: [folded brochure]., circa 1940 (Box 48, Folder 30)
      Item [30] promotes Rumford baking powder in sugarless baking, noting recipes are low in shortening and scarce ingredients, and contain no alum to cause bitterness. Sample recipes: Rumford one-egg cake and orange drop cookies.
  - Box 49
    Rutledge, Ruth Leone.
    Fisher, Marian Cole.
    Farley, W. E.
    Gibbs, Winifred S. (Winifred Stuart), 1871-1928.
    MacPherson, John.
    Crescent Manufacturing Company (Fremont, Ohio)
    Layton Pure Food Company.
    - The Crystal cook book / by Alice Priest Ewell. 127 p., 1905 (Box 49, Folder 1)
      Item [1] promotes Crystal Baking Powder as being a "pure food" superior to other baking powders, especially those containing alum. Includes cooking hints; invalid diet; information on types of baking soda; household economy hints; and illustrations of woman in period dress (cover) and product packaging. Sample recipes: rabbit pie, cherry puffs, and rice gems.
    - Worth reading: cakes without eggs. 16 p., circa 1909 (Box 49, Folder 2)
      Item [2] promotes Crescent Baking Soda as superior to baking powders containing cream-of-tartar, known to cause stomach, kidney, and intestinal disorders. Recipes use baking powder as leavening agent instead of eggs. Includes $500 reward for evidence of injury from using Crescent Baking Powder and illustration of woman in period dress (front cover). Sample recipes: ginger snaps, eggless fruit cake, and cinnamon buns.
    - Reliable recipes, 16th ed. 80 p., circa 1922 (Box 49, Folder 3)
      Item [3] promotes Calumet Baking Powder and supports "alum" in baking powder, citing experts and rebuking Royal Baking Powder's claim to the contrary. Includes illustrations of Chicago plant, laboratories, hospital room for Calumet employees, and product packaging; testimonials from Marian Cole Fisher, noted baking expert and teacher at St. Paul and Mrs. W. E. Farley, 20-time blue ribbon winner, Kentucky State fair; endorsements of housewives bureau and Modern Priscilla Magazine; cooking, household, and cleaning hints; offer for a free children's party book, and index. Sample recipes: custard pie, boiled salad dressing, egg frosting, and Calumet cream puffs. Covers torn and detatched.
    - Cook book, useful information, and interesting data. 64 p., circa 1900s (Box 49, Folder 4)
      Item [4] promotes Davis Baking Powder as superior to brands of baking powder containing cream of tartar. Includes physicians' statements that cream of tartar and soda produce potash salts (poisonous) and that Davis Baking Powder is "healthful." Includes illustrations of Davis manufacturing plant and product packaging; household hints; medical information; comparison of outdated notions with modern and scientific views; measures and weights; and numerous jokes from The foolish dictionary. Sample recipes: Jenny Lind cake, baked pudding, and mutton ragout.
    - Davis Baking Powder cook book: useful information and interesting data. 62 p., circa 1900s (Box 49, Folder 5)
      Item [5] is similar to [4] except for front and back covers, no comparison of outdated vs. modern ideas, and some different recipes. Sample recipes: tomato soup, floating island, and vegetable hash.
    - [Recipes using baking powder: recipe cards]., circa 1900s (Box 49, Folder 6)
      Item [6] contains 2 recipe cards (sugar cookies and hot biscuits) promoting Davis Baking Powder. Includes serving suggestion and product packaging illustrations and offer of complete set of recipe cards for 4 cents in stamps.
    - Davis Baking Powder: selected recipes. 48 p., 1922 (Box 49, Folder 7)
      Item [7] promotes Davis Baking Powder. Includes recipes compiled by Winifred Stuart Gibbs (picture); measurement tables; cooking and household hints; illustrations of factory (interior and exterior), serving suggestions, and product packaging; offer for free Davis recipe book; and index. Sample recipes: daffodil cake, banana fritters and sand cakes.
    - A lesson plan on the muffin mixture and its variations / Ruth Leone Rutledge. 18 p., 1926 (Box 49, Folder 8)
      Item [8] is a teaching guide from R.B. Davis Company for teachers, food demonstrators, and culinary students. Sample recipes: white corn muffins, soy bean muffins, and vanilla sauce.